<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exact relation of the proceedings and transactions of the late Parliament: their beginning and ending. With a briefe account of their expence of the time of their session, and of the acts that were made by them, who were dissolved the 12. Decemb. 1653. As likewise of foure great votes, viz. I. For abolishing the Court of Chancery. II. For a new modell of the law. III. For taking away the power of patrons to make presentations. IV. That innocent negative vote of not agreeing with the report of the committee for tithes. And an account of some reasons of those votes: with a briefe apology in way of vindication of those gentlemen that appeared for the votes from the great out-cry made against them. By L.D. a Member of the late Parliament.</title>
            <author>L. D., member of the late Parliament.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82034</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D52</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E729_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19772</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860738</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860738</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112863</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82034)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112863)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 112:E729[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exact relation of the proceedings and transactions of the late Parliament: their beginning and ending. With a briefe account of their expence of the time of their session, and of the acts that were made by them, who were dissolved the 12. Decemb. 1653. As likewise of foure great votes, viz. I. For abolishing the Court of Chancery. II. For a new modell of the law. III. For taking away the power of patrons to make presentations. IV. That innocent negative vote of not agreeing with the report of the committee for tithes. And an account of some reasons of those votes: with a briefe apology in way of vindication of those gentlemen that appeared for the votes from the great out-cry made against them. By L.D. a Member of the late Parliament.</title>
                  <author>L. D., member of the late Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 27, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Livewell Chapman, at the Crowne in Popes-head Alley.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Febr. [illegible] 14"; the 4 in the imprint date has been crossed out and replaced with a "3".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112863:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EXACT RELATION OF THE PROCEEDINGS AND TRANSACTIONS OF THE LATE PARLIAMENT: Their Beginning and Ending.</p>
            <p>With a briefe account of their Expence of the time of their Seſſion, and of the Acts that were made by them, who were diſſolved the 12. <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1653.</p>
            <p>As likewiſe of foure great Votes, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>I. For aboliſhing the Court of Chancery.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II. For a new Modell of the Law.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>III. For taking away the power of Patrons to make Preſentations.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IV. That innocent negative Vote of not agreeing with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the Committee for Tithes.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And an account of ſome Reaſons of thoſe Votes: With a briefe Apology in way of Vindication of thoſe Gentlemen that appeared for the Votes from the great OUT-CRY made againſt them.</p>
            <p>By <hi>L. D.</hi> a Member of the late PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <bibl>
               <hi>Math. 5.11.</hi>
            </bibl>
            <q>Bleſſed are ye when men revile you, and perſecute you, and ſpeak all manner of evill of you falſly for my Names ſake; rejoyce and be exceeding glad, for great is your reward in Heaven.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Livewell Chapman,</hi> at the Crowne in Popes-head Alley. 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:112863:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112863:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ad not great Blaſphemy reproach and ſcorne beene offered every where unto the holy name of God, his truth, his wayes, his ſervants, by evill men to the great griefe of many fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring God, The following relation and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe had never ſeene the light: the perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſons loaded with great reproach and ſcandall, could in regard of themſelves, have beene contented to have borne all patiently with ſilence: and left the clearing of their innocency to the moſt righteous God. It is no new thing in the world for good men to bee reproached for well doing, and to have no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reward for endeavoring to do their Countrey ſervice, and laboring to take off their heavy oppreſſions and grievances, then to be counted evill doers: what is generally reported, is as eaſily beleeved and taken for truth though it be never ſo falſe: great lightneſſe and vanity attending perſons as is too too evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. That one part of the Houſe would have deſtroyed all the Miniſtry, the good as well as the bad (paſſes for currant) when as they were onely againſt that old corrupt unequall, burthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and debate making way of their maintenance by Tithes: In which way beſide other things, many a good ſoule hath onely <hi>20</hi> or <hi>30</hi> l. <hi>per Ann.</hi> to keepe him and his alive; and others of leſſe deſert have <hi>300</hi> or <hi>400</hi> l. <hi>per Ann.</hi> or more, they thinking ſome more equall and leſſe burthenſome way might be found out and provided; and that their wives and children
<pb facs="tcp:112863:3"/>
might have had alowance for their ſubſiſtance alſo when they were dead: many alſo were againſt their ſtanding on that old Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh foot of account as now they do, as a part of the old Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, judging it reaſon that as Archbiſhops and Biſhops, Deans, and Prebends, &amp;c. were removed as Antichriſtian; ſo Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Vicars, Curats, Rectors, Donatives, and Incumbents, (strangers to the Goſpel) ſhould be taken away alſo being of the ſame ſtamp: and that all faithfull Teachers and Preachers of the truth and Goſpel, ſhould by Law ſtand upon a more Gospel account, and their outward intereſt ſecured unto them accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly: a ſhort Bill being by them offered for that purpoſe but refuſed; whether this amounteth to the deſtroying the Godly Miniſtry, or whether they were their enemies or rather their friends in it, they may pleaſe to conſider. Reader, if thou thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt that thou art come to Canaan the land of reſt, and that there is attayned unto the full end aimed at and intended by Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, in anſwer of all thoſe mighty workes and wonders (neare unto miracles) that hee hath wrought in theſe Lands: If thou thinkſt there is already the harveſt of all that treaſure ſpent, and blood ſpilt in the late Warres, then rejoyce and bee glad: but if thou judgeſt God intended greater and more high things then yet thou haſt ſeene, in way of removing wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and oppreſſion, and advancing juſtice and righteouſneſse, then beleeve, and wait and pray; ſo adviſeth hee that is a well wiſher to the intereſt of the Lord Chriſt, the welfare of the Saints, and the proſperity of the common wealth of England.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>L. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:112863:3"/>
            <head>AN EXACT RELATION OF THE PROCEEDINGS and Tranſactions of the late Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, their beginning and ending: with a briefe account of the expence of their time while they ſate; and the <hi>Acts that were made by them, who were diſſolved the</hi> 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>of</hi> December. 1653.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Parliament that ſate ſo long, and had ſo many changes and alterations, and yet was preſerved and continued: Was a Counſell that God did highly honour in making of them Inſtruments of very great things, many of them being very good things, as to the freedome and profit of the people; Amongſt which the Change of the Government from Kingly to that of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, may worthily be mentioned, as not of the leaſt, but of the greateſt, both to Religions Intereſt, and the Civill Benefit of all good men.</p>
            <p>But long ſitting Contracted dulneſſe, and a kinde of Indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to goe on any farther to perfect the worke which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine providence had carried them on in wonderfully: Many of them minding more the greatning of themſelves, rather
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:112863:4"/>
then righting the wronged, and releiving the oppreſſed peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and performing their promiſes to them; ſo not proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to perfect the worke of Juſtice and freedome ſo happily begun and carried on by them, as Inſtruments in the hand o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God. They became low in the hearts and eſteem of good peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and divine providence ſo ordering of it, (without which nothing cometh to paſſe) they were diſſolved.</p>
            <p>And upon an high Account for Godlineſſe, and the Love of the truth, and cauſe of God, and Intereſt of his people, others were called together out of the Countries and Cities reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, who aſſembling at the place and time appointed, after a large Speech made unto them concerning the ground of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving the former Counſell, and calling of this; There was delivered unto them an Inſtrument in Parchment under ſeale; delivering the whole power of the Nation or Common-wealth into their hands, to take care of, and to governe for their good. It is very obſervable that of all that were ſo cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen and ſummoned to appeare for the end aforeſaid, being one hundred and fortie perſons, there were but two that refuſed the call and worke; ſo unanimous a Concurrence was there found as to the ſervice: Though they knew well their call was not according to ancient formalitie, and the way of the Nation. There ſeemed to be two Reaſons wherein there was ſatisfaction: Firſt, that divine providence had caſt it on them, without their ſeeking in the leaſt; Secondly, the neceſſitie, as the caſe of the Common-wealth ſtood of having ſome to Act and carry on Affaires in way of Government, till there might be an Attayner to a better way of ſettlement, by the Choice of the good people of this Nation, which was not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied to be their juſt right, and dearly purchaſed libertie.</p>
            <p>It was great ſatisfaction and encouragement to ſome, that their Names had been preſented as to that ſervice by the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and other Godly perſons: And withall, becauſe they were to undergoe the Trouble but one yeare, or little more: And ſo long they were willing to ſerve their Country freely, to their beſt Abilities, looking for no reward.</p>
            <p>The fourth of <hi>July,</hi> 1653. thoſe thus Aſſembled and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powered, did adjourne themſelves from <hi>Whitehall</hi> to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament-Houſe,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:112863:4"/>
to meet the next morning at eight of the Clocke, and then to begin with ſeeking God by prayer: which accordingly they did, and the ſervice was performed by the Members amongſt themſelves, eight or ten ſpeaking in prayer to God; and ſome briefly from the Word; Much of the preſence of Chriſt, and of his Spirit, appearing that day, to the great gladding of the hearts of many; ſome affirming they never injoyed ſo much of the Spirit and preſence of Chriſt in any of the meetings and exerciſes of Religion in all their lives, as they did that day. In the Evening of that day M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Francis Rouſe</hi> was called to the Chaire, and choſen Speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: and then the Houſe was adjourned to the next day: when the Houſe appoynted to pray againe three or foure dayes after; which accordingly was done by the Members; principally by ſuch as had not don ſervice before; when alſo the Lord Generall was preſent; and it was a very Comfortable day. But after the Houſe had ſpent the firſt day in prayer, and were the next day met againe, after prayer, which was daily performed by one Member or other, as they were found free to performe it; They then proceeded to call over the Houſe; Read and laid up the Inſtrument of their Impowering, choſe a Clerke, and after a Sergeant at Armes, and choſe a Committee to Conſider what Officers and Attendants were neceſſary to be taken in; and to Conſider of the Fees and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laries of ſuch as ſhould be Imployed; which accordingly was done, and Confirmed by the Houſe: Charge being given to the Committee that care ſhould be taken that none but ſuch as feared God ſhould be Imployed. About this Time there was a great Debate what name they ſhould give themſelves to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by, in as much as their cal was looked on as extraordinary; Divers Titles were propoſed; but at laſt being put to the vote it was carried; <hi>To call themſelves by the name of the Parliament of the Common-wealth of England.</hi> The lowneſſe and innocencie of the Title, having little of earthly glory or boaſting in it, induced ſome to give their vote for that; though others were much againſt it. The firſt thing that was done was a ſolemne Declaration to the good people of this Common-wealth, and to all the world of owning themſelves a Parliament, and the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:112863:5"/>
Supream Power of this Nation. Which was drawne up by a Committee, and then read and paſſed in the Houſe; In which ſpecious things are held forth, of the goodneſſe of God to the people of theſe Nations, with Intimation of what our Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours ſhould be, for their good: ſtirring them up earneſtly to prayer, and ſeeking of God: which ſeemed to be well reliſhed by all good people.</p>
            <p>Then there was a proceed to chooſe the Councell of State, of the number of Thirtie one perſons; which accordingly was done. The Powers and Inſtructions read and paſſed, It ſo fell out that the great grievance of Tythes was taken on and debated three or four dayes, but with little ſucceſſe, for where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as all the Houſe for the moſt part were ſencible that it was a grievance fit to be removed. The difference was, ſome would not give way to the remove of it, till ſome other thing were provided to be ſett in the roome of it: Others would have it removed as a grievance in the firſt place; and then to make proviſion as God ſhould direct. In the Debate, difference was made betwixt Impropriators, and that which was otherwiſe; and all ſeemed free and willing that Impropriators ſhould be ſatisfied the value: And therefore upon the chooſing of a Committee for Tythes; onely that of Incumbants was to be conſidered of.</p>
            <p>The Houſe after much time ſpent as afore, waved it till a further time and better leiſure: Then the Houſe was metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dized into ſeveral Committees, for the better diſpatch of bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, ſo as none might be idle, but all employed in publick ſervice; beſide the Councel of State, ſix or ſeven Committees were choſen and ſet to work, <hi>The Committee for the Army, The Committee for Priſons, and Priſoners, The Committee for Regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Law, The Committee for Juſtices, and for the poor, The Committee for Publick Debts, The Committee for the Scotch and Iriſh Affaires, The Committee for Petitions;</hi> which Committees ſate dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and took great paines, morning and evening, almoſt every day in the week, to diſpatch buſineſſe, and make things ready for the Houſe: And many things were fitted and prepared, of which hereafter.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Lilburn</hi> about this time Petitioned the Houſe, then his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112863:5"/>
Wife Petitioned, after ſome of <hi>Buckinghmſhire,</hi> and alſo <hi>Hert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordſhire;</hi> likewiſe ſome in and about <hi>London:</hi> Laſtly, ſome that called themſelves young men, and Apprentices, who deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered a high and peremptory Petition in his behalfe; all w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> occaſioned much debate and expence of time: The young mens Petition was voted ſcandalous, and they ordered to be taken into cuſtody, and accordingly ſix of them were committed, one in a few dayes being ſick, the Houſe diſcharged him; the five Petitioning, having been in cuſtody ſome dayes, and having been ſomething ſtiffe, refuſing to tell their names, inſtead of being releaſed, were ordered to be ſent to <hi>Bridewell,</hi> there to be kept to hard labour, and accordingly they were ſent, and kept there, and after ſome time they being ſome of them ſick, and having Petitioned twice, four of the five were by Order of the Houſe releaſed, the other remaineth Priſoner to this day; the onely high piece of Juſtice the Houſe did all the time of their ſitting, and wherein there could not be much of honour, for it was but as the <hi>Lyon</hi> trampling on the <hi>Mouſe.</hi> This buſineſſe of Mr. <hi>Lilburne</hi> receiving and anſwering the Petitions before mentioned, concerning himſelfe and the Apprentices Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for their Liberty, ſpent very much time, and held many ſharp debates; ſome Members of the Houſe earneſtly moving to have had his Tryal ſuſpended, and the Act called in Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by which he was Baniſhed, and made a Felon, that the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the cauſe might be looked into; which they profeſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine and againe they did not doe it ſo much in the favour of Mr. <hi>Lilburn,</hi> as in the right of themſelves and their poſterities, and all <hi>Engliſh</hi> men, which they judged highly concerned therein. But other Gentlemen of note being very oppoſite, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing came of the whole but expence of time, and loſſe of the love &amp; affections of many good people, whoſe Petitions were denied; his Trial going on, as ſome in the Houſe had ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, ſo it came to paſſe, he was by the Jury acquitted, to the looſing the love of ſome, and to the ſcorne and contempt by others.</p>
            <p>By this time many matters were fitted and prepared by the Committees, who made their daily reports. The Councel of State having the preheminence to be firſt heard, divers things
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112863:6"/>
were offered by them, ſome of which had been conſidered of by them in the interval of Parliament; many things paſſed and were diſpatched of what they reported, and which other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees did likewiſe report, which ſpent not a little time. Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe came on ſo faſt from Committees, which did cauſe ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving which ſhould be firſt heard, and much time loſt thereby. There were many particular things ordered and diſpatched by the Houſe, as <hi>The relieving the ſufferings of many by fires in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall parts of the Nation; ſome their grievances redreſſed; ſome their Petitions and deſires granted; ſome had obſtructions in their Purchaſes removed by the Houſe.</hi> The buſineſſe of providing mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys (all other things ever giving way to that) occaſioned expence of much time, and great debate of wayes and means to that end. The Fights at Sea coming to knowledge by Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, the reading of them, the acknowledging Gods goodneſſe, and praiſing of his holy name, the taking care to provide for the ſick and maimed, the relieving the Widowes of ſuch whoſe Husbands were ſlaine, the honouring with rewards the Chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and Commanders, with the beſtowing ſeveral ſums of money on the widows and Children of ſuch Captains as were ſlain in the Fight, in conſideration of their loſſe of ſuch Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands and Fathers: All which were things juſt and honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but not done without expence of time. The diſpatch of Ambaſſadors to forreign parts, as to <hi>Turkie,</hi> and to <hi>Sweden,</hi> their Letters of Credence, and Commiſſions ſigned and ſealed; the receipt of Letters from <hi>Switzerland,</hi> and other free States, the reading of them and returning Anſwers, may be reckoned into the expence of time. The Councel of State choſen a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time by the Box or Glaſſe where every one put in his paper of Names, and thoſe that had moſt Votes carried it, ſpent more then one whole day.</p>
            <p>To omit very many things, toward the end of the Houſe's ſitting, the buſineſſe of the <hi>Exciſe</hi> came on, where about three dayes were ſpent in paſſing the Rates particularly by Vote. The <hi>Old and New Drapery, Hats, Capps,</hi> and <hi>Tobacco-pipes,</hi> were by Vote exempted from the duty of Exciſe: The Bill follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Order of the Rates, was very large of about eighty ſheets of paper, ſpent one whole day in the hearing of it read; and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112863:6"/>
there appeared ſo many ſnares and difficulties in it as to trade, as was judged no way fit to be put on a people that expected freedome as the price of their blood and treaſure, by them ſpent in the late war: whereupon it was by general conſent waved and laid aſide. There were divers Bils prepared by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Committees, ſome of which were read in the Houſe, and others offered to have them read, but other buſineſſe hindered, as, <hi>A Bill for conſtituting a Committee for Advance of Trade, A Bill for Work-houſes, and providing for the poor.</hi> Divers <hi>Bills for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulation of the Law, and making of it leſſe chargeable to the people, and more expeditions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There were ſeverrll Acts paſſed by the Houſe, in time of their ſitting, the perticulars here follow. <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 An Act for the Committee of the Army, and Treaſurers of War.</p>
            <p n="2">2 An Act for conſtituting Commiſſioners for ordering and managing the Admiralty and Navy.</p>
            <p n="3">3 An Act for the ſettling the Court of Admiralty; much time ſpent in fixing on Judges.</p>
            <p n="4">4 An Act for taking away Fines on Original Writs, which was as ſome knowing Gentlemen of worth in the Houſe affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, to the ſaving of the people of this Common-wealth, an hundred and twenty thouſand pound <hi>per annum,</hi> only ten or twelve thouſand pound thereof coming to the State.</p>
            <p n="5">5 An Act touching the ſeveral Receipts of the Revenue and Treaſuries of the Common-wealth, and the bringing them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one Treaſury.</p>
            <p n="6">6 An Act for Marriages, and the regiſtring of them; as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Births and Burials; much time ſpent in the debate about Marriages, there being many nicities and difficult caſes rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to that ſubject.</p>
            <p n="7">7 An Act for the more ſpeedy bringing in of the Arrears of the Exciſe, and ſetling Commiſſioners to that end.</p>
            <p n="8">8 An Act concerning the Planters of <hi>Tobacco</hi> in <hi>Glouceſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> and elſwhere.</p>
            <p n="9">9 An Act to continue the receipt of the Exciſe til the 29 of <hi>December</hi> laſt.</p>
            <p n="10">10 An Act additional and explanatory for the ſale of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112863:7"/>
remaining Fee farm-rents, and finiſhing the whole buſineſſe.</p>
            <p n="11">11 An Act for ſetling <hi>Ireland,</hi> and making it a part of the Common-wealth; and ſatisfying the Adventurers and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers with Lands; which Act being very large and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive, took many dayes Debate before it could be paſſed as a Law.</p>
            <p n="12">12 An Act for the relief of Creditors and poor Priſoners; the fruit of it hath ſhewed the worth of it, three hundred poor ſtarving ſouls having been freed thereby, in and about <hi>London:</hi> a Law ſo juſt and honourable, as <hi>England</hi> hath ſeen few better, which paſſed not without ſerious debate.</p>
            <p n="13">13 An Act for Accounts, and clearing publick Debts, and for the diſcovery of fraud and concealment of any thing due to the Common-wealth.</p>
            <p n="14">14 An Act impowering the Committee of the Army to ſtate and determine the accounts of all Souldiers and others em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed by them, for moneys by them received from the 26 of <hi>March,</hi> 1647. until the 25 of <hi>July,</hi> 1653.</p>
            <p n="15">15 An Act for redreſſe of delayes, and miſchiefs, ariſing by Writs of error, and Writs of falſe judgement in ſeveral caſes.</p>
            <p n="16">16 An Act for repealing of a branch of an Act of the late Parliament, intituled, <hi>An Act for ſubſcribing the Ingagement;</hi> which was much to the eaſe and profit of the people, and to the loſſe of the Lawyers.</p>
            <p n="17">17 An Act for the regulating the making of <hi>Stuffes</hi> in the County of <hi>Norwich</hi> and <hi>Norfolke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18 An Act for a High Court of Juſtice, coſt indeed but one dayes time the reading, debate, and paſſing for a Law, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the great haſt ſome Gentlemen made, pretending great danger to themſelves, and the Common-wealth, ſo as no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons could prevaile to have it recommitted as ſome deſired; or that the Acts for Treaſons might be read, that the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners were to proceed upon, as others moved to have them: nor yet that the Bil might be ingroſſed, being to be a Law that concerned life, for then it could not have paſſed til the next day, when ſome that were perceived that day abſent, being praying at the <hi>Black Friers,</hi> might be preſent, and hinder, as it is likely they feared, the paſſing of it; which had they done,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112863:7"/>
they had ſaved much the credit of the Counſel, for to wiſe men it ſeemed a very weak piece, and experience hath (thanks be to God) ſhewn there was not that ſudden danger as ſome Gentlemen ſuggeſted, that did not let to ſay (in anſwer to thoſe that would have had it ingroſſed againſt the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning) <hi>That they knew not but by that time they might have their Throats cut.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="19">19 An Act for Deofforiſtation, and improvement of the Forreſts, and of the Honours, Mannors, Lands, and Tenements within the limits and perambulations of the ſame, heretofore belonging to the King, Queen, and Prince: a very large Act, and comprehenſive in the perticulars; wherein the old Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers of the <hi>Cuſtome-houſe,</hi> that lent the old King money to make War with the <hi>Scots,</hi> were admitted to have their old Debts made Publick Faith to double on, to the ſum of two hundred ſeventy ſix thouſand pounds, to the end to be ſure to have money againſt the Spring: It was complied with, and ſome very eminent and wiſe Gentlemen made others believe there was no queſtion but the money would be provided ready againſt the times, though other Members of leſſe note, tould the Houſe what they thought, even as it is come to paſſe.</p>
            <p n="20">20 An Act confirming to the Purchaſers of Sir <hi>John Stowels</hi> Lands, what they had purchaſed of the State.</p>
            <p n="21">21 An Act for an Aſſeſment at the rate of one hundred and twenty thouſand pound a Month, for ſix Moneths, from the twenty-fifth of <hi>December,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred fifty and three, to the twenty-fourth of <hi>June</hi> then next enſuing, for the maintenance of the Armies and Navy of this Common-wealth, being a very large Act, and that which took up ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dayes in the debate and paſſing of it, there being a deſire if poſſible it might have been to have abated ſomething of that ſum, and that it might be laid equally: Many Votes paſſed, and very ſharp debates, by reaſon of the great inequality that was evident in the laying of the Tax, ſome Countreys bearing beyond their proportion, and ſome much leſſe, which made the burthen more grievous then otherwiſe it would be: When after many dayes ſpent in the modelizing of the Bill, and it came to be paſſed, ſome Gentlemen gave their reaſons why
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:112863:8"/>
they could not give their <hi>Yea</hi> to paſſe it for a Law, for the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe that was in it (and ſomething elſe) which had been laid forth in the debate. The great unequality be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt County and County, City and City, Hundred and Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and ſo of perticular Eſtates, ſome paying but two or three ſhillings the pound, and others four or five, yea ſome ten or twelve ſhillings for their reall Eſtate, beſide what they paid for their perſonall: In which ſome of <hi>London</hi> paſſionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly complained of their being over-rated, they paying eight thouſand pound a Month, the fifteenth part of the whole Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſment of the Common-wealth: when as they with great confidence affirmed, that they were not the fortieth part of the Common-wealth in value, as their caſe now was. The Act ingroſſed, and the Queſtion being put, the <hi>No's</hi> (as to the making it a Law that very day) had they been proſecuted to the pole, had hazzarded the paſſing of it; It having been ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly preſſed that it might be amended at the Table, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>committed to be amended againſt the next day.</p>
            <p>A Gentleman that firſt moved to have the Houſe give u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that morning they were Diſſolved, made this one of his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons why he could ſit no longer with his fellows, becauſe of their dealing ſo diſ-ingenuouſly with the Army; ſome other Gentlemen having ſpoken to the ſame account; but as to this thoſe that gave their <hi>No's</hi> in the Vote againſt the then paſſing of the Bill upon the account before, can ſay they never were in arms againſt the Parliament and Army, nor were ever in <hi>Oxford</hi> or any other Garriſon that ſtood in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to them. And for their conſtant cordial affection to them, they may ſafely ſay without boaſting, they have been but a very little behind them that have been the higheſt and beſt affected in the Nation, what ever thoſe Gentlemen pleaſe to ſay: To indeavour to have the Aſſeſment equally laid and born, tended much to the Armies good rather then hurt, whereby they might continue to injoy the love and affection of the people unto them.</p>
            <p n="22">22 An Act for the continuing of the Priviledges and Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of the County of <hi>Lancaster.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="23">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:112863:8"/>23 An Act touching Idiots and Lunaticks.</p>
            <p n="24">24 An Act for inabling Commiſſioners of Parliament for compounding with DELINQUENTS, to diſpoſe of two parts of the Lands and Eſtates of Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants, for the benefit of the Common-wealth. An Act that coſt much time in the Debate of it, for that ſome Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men fearing it amounted to the Toleration of Popery, did ſtrongly oppoſe it, and cauſed it to be ſo modelized as that it was never like to attain the end aimed at, as ſome then declared: Of which experience now can beſt declare and ſpeak.</p>
            <p n="25">25. A ſecond Act for the Conſtituting Commiſſioners for ordering and mannaging of the Affaires of the Admiraltie and Navie.</p>
            <p n="26">26. An Act for the better and more effectuall diſcoverie of Theeves and high-way-men.</p>
            <p>There was alſo a Bill brought in and Read and Debated for the Uniting of <hi>Scotland</hi> to the Common-wealth of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as a part of it, with equal priviledges: which ſpent two or three days Debate in a Grand Committee of the whole Houſe, before it was ordered to be Ingroſſed, being a thing of very great weight and concernment, being ingroſſed it lay ready on the Table to be read and paſſed. But the <hi>Highlanders</hi> putting the Country into diſtemper, it was not put to be paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for a Law while the Houſe continued.</p>
            <p>By this time it will appeare the Houſe was not altogether Idle, nor at a ſtand in their worke, ſo as there was need to have them diſſolved on that ſcore. Indeed much more might have been done and proceeded in, if there had not been ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that did lett. The two Great Grievances of the Law and Tythes, had ſuch friends in the Houſe; as that when ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of thoſe things came into Debate, the Houſe was as divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into two parts; The one very Indulgent, ſtill pleading and making defence in their behalfe; The other Indeavouring the redreſſe of them. Great Counſells agree not in all things preſently, yet is that no good Ground of their diſſolution; That the Houſe was not Idle, nor at a ſtand, nor in an Incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:112863:9"/>
to doe the worke of the Nation. Though ſo divided as aforeſaid, may beſide what appeareth alreadie, be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther taken knowledge of by theſe Inſuing Votes which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
            <p>There were foure great Votes, that paſſed in the time of the ſitting of the Houſe, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ſome Intereſts were much diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at, and they paſſed not without great Debate.</p>
            <p>Firſt, A Vote for the Aboliſhing and taking away the Court of Chancery.</p>
            <p>Secondly, A Vote for a new Body or Modell of the Law.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, A Vote to take away the power of Patrons to make preſentations.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, That Innocent Negative Vote of not agreeing with the Report of the Committee for Tythes, Touching what they Reported, as the beſt way to eject ſcandalous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and ignorant Miniſters, &amp;c. Upon which followed pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently the diſſolution of the Houſe.</p>
            <p>A little of each of theſe, becauſe of the great duſt that is rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, to the blinding of ſome, and inraging of others, againſt them that ſought not themſelves, but the good of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth in generall, and no private or particular In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts.</p>
            <p>Firſt, For the Chancery, It was looked on as a great grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, one of the greateſt in the Nation, ſo many horrible things were affirmed of it by Members of the Houſe, as thoſe that were or had a minde to be Advocates for it, had little to ſay on the behalfe of it, and ſo at the end of one dayes De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, the queſtion being put, it was voted downe.</p>
            <p>For Delatories, Chargeableneſſe, and a facultie of letting Bloud the people in the purſe-veine, even to their utter pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing and undoing, as by what was ſpoken and affirmed at the Debate. That Court may compare (if not ſurpaſſe) any Court in the world; It was Confidently affirmed by knowing Gentlemen of worth; that there were depending in that Court, Twentie three thouſand Cauſes; That ſome of them had been there depending five, ſome ten, ſome twentie, ſome thirtie yeares and more; That there had been
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:112863:9"/>
ſpent in Cauſes many hundred, nay thouſands of pounds, to the ruine, nay utter undoing of many families; That no Ship almoſt (to wit, Cauſe) that ſayled in the Sea of the Law, but firſt or laſt putting into that Port, and if they made any conſiderable ſtay there, they ſuffered ſo much loſſe, as the Remedy was as bad as the Diſeaſe; That what was Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered one day, was Contradicted the next, ſo as in ſome Cauſes there had been five hundred Orders, and farre more as ſome affirmed. That when the purſes of the Clients be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be emptie, and their ſpirits a little cooled; then by a Reference to ſome Gentlemen in the Countrey, the Cauſe ſo long depending, at ſo great Charge, came to be ended, ſo as ſome did looke on it as it now is, as a Myſterie of wickedneſſe, and a ſtanding Cheat.</p>
            <p>How ſad a thing is it that after ſuch Appearances of God in the Land, ſuch a Court, in ſuch a way of practiſe, ſhould be continued, to greaten the Retayners to it, and practiſers in it, by the ruine of others, eating the fatt and ſweet of other mens labours and eſtates. It is to be hoped ſuch wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe is not long lived; How did good people rejoyce when they heard of that Vote, and how ſad and ſorrowfull were the Lawyers and Clarkes, for the feare of the loſſe of their great <hi>Diana</hi> may be remembred: with their great joy and making Bonfiers, and drinking Sacke when they were delivered from their feares by the diſſolution of the late Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
            <p>The Committee for the Regulating of the Law, in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of the Vote, brought in a Bill for the Taking away the ſaid Court: But for that there was not proviſion made for the future, and for the Cauſes then depending, altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; It was oppoſed by thoſe Gentlemen that had no mind it ſhould be taken away; And ſo it came to be waved and layd aſide, and the Committee ordered to bring in a Bill that might doe all.</p>
            <p>The Members of that Committee, having many of them occaſion to be abſent in the Countrey, in fetching up and ſettling their Families before Winter. Nothing was done
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112863:10"/>
till toward the Terme, when a Bill was brought in and read in the Houſe; That was looked on by many as the waſhing of the Blackamore, or pruining or lopping evill branches, where three or foure in a little time will come in ſtead of one cutt off. Upon Debate it came to the Queſtion, and was carried in the Negative, and caſt out.</p>
            <p>Then ſhortly after another Bill was brought in and read, which to very many ſeemed to be a ſetting up of two Courts, rather then a caſting downe one, and an eſtabliſhing of the Chancery, rather then a Taking of it away: Some Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of great Note of the Long Robe, had a hand in it; That it is likely will never ſpoyle their owne Trade; The Bill by very many, after a long and ſharpe Debate, was judged ſhort of the end aimed at, and being put to the Queſtion, it paſſed in the Negative, and was alſo caſt out; At which ſome of thoſe Gentlemen aforeſaid, were very much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed.</p>
            <p>The Term by this time was begun, and the people not eaſed as was hoped it would have been, at which thoſe Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers that carried the Vote for putting down that corrupt Court, were ſorely vexed and troubled, who took little delight to come through the Hall, and to ſee the corrupt Trade going on; ſome of them moved to have had the Court ſuſpended for three weeks or a month, till ſomthing might be done in it, but it was not conſented unto, or thought fit, and ſo the Term and trade of the Law went on, and the Committee went to work again: and by this time ſome other Members of that Committee, that were not ſuch great zealots for the upholding of that Court, were come to Town, ſo as a Bill was modelized and prepared, which they of the Committee thought would anſwer the end, and be to the liking of the Houſe; in which was provided for the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king down the Court, and for the diſpatch of the Cauſes depending, and providing for the future in a ſummary way, ſo as any ordinary cauſe might be determined and ended for twenty or forty ſhillings, and in a very ſhort time, and much ſtrife and going to Law prevented.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:112863:10"/>But the Houſe being full of buſineſs there was no oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to tender it, and ſo they let it alone til a fitter time and more leiſure.</p>
            <p>If a Copy of that intended Bill were Printed, it might be judged what their intentions were; for that after it was got in and twice read in the Houſe in one day.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Vote which was for a new body of the Law, paſſed not without a large Debate; the Clerk in drawing up the Queſtion, put the word <hi>Body</hi> in ſtead of <hi>Model,</hi> which ſome Members for the paſſing of the Vote before and after, deſired to have had altered: but others, lovers of the Law as now it is, oppoſed the alteration of the word, being very angry at the Vote, and ſo it went as it was, with ſome ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſadvantage, by means of the word <hi>Body,</hi> which ſome of thoſe aforeſaid being angry, would needs fancy, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly reported, as if it were intended to deſtroy the Law, and take away the Laws we had been fighting for all this while as our birth-right and inheritance.</p>
            <p>And ſuch a noiſe was made about it, that made many be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that the Houſe was modelized of Monſters, rather then men of reaſon and judgment.</p>
            <p>There were very ſober and moderate Gentlemen, in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of all men, that concurred heartily in this Vote, ſuch as upon whom little blemiſh will ſtick.</p>
            <p>The Reaſons, or ſome of them that were alledged in the Debate, producing this Vote, was the intricacy, uncertainty, and incongruity in many things with the word of God, and right reaſon, in the Laws as now they are.</p>
            <p>Firſt, whereas the Laws ought to be eaſie, plain, and ſhort, ſo as they that were to be ſubject to them, and have benefit by them, might be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble to know and underſtand them in ſome good meaſure.</p>
            <p>They are now ſo voluminous, and thereby Intricate and uncertaine, darke and concealed, as few are able to come to the knowledge of them. Thoſe of the profeſſion of the Law differing in very many caſes, what the Law is, and being of ſeverall opinions about this and the other thing: And then how ſhould others, though highly concerned be able to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:112863:11"/>
them; and their Intereſt therein contained. There being ſo many Law-Bookes of great Bulke, ſo many old muſtie Records, Reports, and Book-Caſes; As that after the time ſpent in School-learning, the reſt of the Time of the flower of a mans yeares, would be little enough to reade them over, and peruſe them.</p>
            <p>And beſide, thoſe Records and Book-Caſes are very ill Guides or Lights to goe by, for who knoweth the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances that did attend them, which alters oft times the whole Caſe; who knoweth whither in thoſe Caſes, bribery did not make the Judgement, or the powerfullneſſe of ſome great man, or the love or hatred of the Judge, or the Negligence or Corruption of the Advocate. And beſides, in thoſe Law-Caſes, ſome preſidents are directly Contrary to others; And an Advocate or Counſell alledgeth one Caſe or Report, and another another: and then the Judge followeth which he pleaſeth: how Arbitrary is the Law in this Caſe? and at what uncertainty are the great Intereſts and proprieties of men?</p>
            <p>Beſide, how various are the Cuſtoms, which notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing paſſeth for Law? Uſually unknown, but to ſome old men of the place, which though it be never ſo unrighteous and unreaſonable, <hi>Time out of minde,</hi> carries it. How bulky and voluminous are the Statute Books? and of ſo great a price as few are able to buy them, and ſo large that few can ſpare time to read them, to know their right, and how they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in them; and yet they muſt be judged, and ſtand or fall by them. And many times ſome old muſty Statute of a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years old, and more imprinted, is found and made uſe of by ſome crafty Lawyer, to the undoing of an honeſt man that meant no hurt, nor knew any thing at all of the danger. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſomething held forth to this effect, the Vote was carried for a New body or model of the Law, and a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee choſen to that end, who met often, and had the helpe of ſome Gentlemen of worth, that have deſerved well of their Countrey, being true Patriots: who liked well the thing, as very uſefull and deſireable: It being not a deſtroying of the LAW, or putting it downe,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:112863:11"/>
as ſome ſcandalouſly reported: But a reducing the whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, juſt, and good Laws, into a Body, from them that are uſeleſs, and out of date; ſuch as concerned the Biſhops, and holy Church (ſo called) and were made in favour of Kings, and the luſts of great men, of which there are very many: the Law of God being eyed, and right Reaſon looked unto in all: there being ſome of the Laws that are contrary to both: as the putting men to death for Theft, The ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the lives of men for Murther, under the notion and name of Manſlaughter, a term and diſtinction not found in the righteous Law of God: And that unreaſonable Law, that if a Waggon or Cart, &amp;c. driven by the owner, or ſome other, with never ſo great care and endeavour, fall, and kill any perſon, the owner, though it were his own ſon or ſervant could no way help it, ſhall looſe his Horſe and Waggon by the prophane and ſuperſtitious name of Deo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dand; And the owners of the goods ſhall looſe them alſo upon the ſame account, though they were as innocent as <hi>Abel:</hi> other inſtances might alſo be given.</p>
            <p>The way the Committee took in order to their work which muſt needs be elaborate; was by reducing the ſeverall Laws to their proper heads, to which they did belong: and ſo modelizing or imbodying of them, taking knowledge of the nature of them, and what the Law of God ſaid in the caſe, and now agreeable to right reaſon they were; likewiſe how proportionable the puniſhment was to the offence or crime; and wherein there ſeemed any thing either deficient, or exceſſive, to offer a ſupply and remedie, in order to recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the whole: The Committee began with Criminals; Treaſon being the higheſt, they conſidered the kinds: what was meet to be a judged Treaſon, in a free Common-wealth; and what was meet to be the puniſhment of Grand and Pettie Treaſon: Then they proceeded to Murther, the kinds of it, and what was to be ſo ajudged, and the puniſhment thereof. The like they intended concerning Theft, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to have aſertained and ſecured propertie; As alſo the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cecutive part of the Law: ſo as a perſon ſhould not need to looſe, or part with one propertie, to ſecure and keep another,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:112863:12"/>
as now it is: Perſons being forced to looſe or part with the propertie of their Cow, to keep the property of their Horſe; and one peice or parcel of Land to preſerve and keep ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Which Body of Law when modelized, was to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to the Houſe to be conſidered of, and paſſed by them as they ſhould ſee cauſe: A work great, and of high and great eſteem with many, for the great fruit and benefit that would come by it: By which means the great volumes of Law would come to be reduced into the bigneſs of a pocket book, as it is proportionable in <hi>New England</hi> and elſewhere: A thing of ſo great worth and benefit as <hi>England</hi> is not yet worthy of, nor likely in a ſhort time to be ſo bleſſed as to injoy. And this being the true End and Endeavour of thoſe Members that laboured in that Committee, it is ſubmitted to every godly (and rationall) man in the Nation, whether (as is moſt falſly and wickedly reported, and charged upon perſons acting in ſo much love to their Countrey) their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours tended to deſtroying the whole Laws, and pulling them up by the roots.</p>
            <p>The third Vote was the taking away of patrons Preſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which thing is one of the ſtrong holds of Sathan: At the paſſing of this Vote ſome Gentlemen were greatly offended; pretending it was a deſtroying, and taking away proprietie: The Gentleman that moved firſt to have the Houſe diſſolved, made this one of his great Reaſons why he could ſit no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger with his fellows, being very contious, like thoſe that ſtumble at a ſtraw, and yet leap over a block: Tith mint, and Commin, and neglect the great things of the Law: This Vote after a ſharp Debate was carried in, in which very ſober Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen concurred, ſuch as are not blemiſhed, as Sectaries, or Levellers: Though they had of this kind o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> propertie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſome two or three a peece that out of conſcience for the better advance of the knowledge of the Goſpel, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the Lord Chriſt, they were willing to part with their right herein.</p>
            <p>The nature of this propriety may be a little minded, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the great outcry that is every where made, Oh the Parliament men, many of them are ſuch as would deſtroy all property: As if they had none themſelves, when as though
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:112863:12"/>
all of them had not very bulkie Eſtates, yet they had free Eſtates, and were not of broken Fortunes, or ſuch as owed great ſummes of money, ten thouſand pounds and more, and thoſe to whom they were ſo in debt knew not how to get a penny of it, but ſtood in need of priviledg and protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as formerly it hath been: The nature of this property looked into, and conſidered, will appear to be partly of an earthly, and partly of ſpiritual nature; Theſe two mixed and twiſted together, make up this right or property: of having power to preſent a Perſon to be Miniſter there. To have the earthly, or civil advantag'd Tithes, and offerings, and Gleab land if there be any; and to have the more religious, or ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual right and Intereſt, the cure and care of ſouls, of all living within that circumference called a Pariſh, and to have the right to officiat to God, and man there; And is not this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty worth the ſtanding for? to be Lord Patron, ſo as he may open the dore to whom he pleaſeth; And be ſure he let in ſuch a one as will comply and ſerve his Intereſt, and wink at his vitious courſes, and not vex and diſquiet his greatneſs by tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him of his faults, as ſomtime <hi>John Baptist</hi> did <hi>Herod;</hi> or as thoſe, which prophanely they call Puritans, and Sectarian Miniſters uſe to do.</p>
            <p>But ſeeing to ſell this property, were no leſs then the ſin of Simony, what worldly advantage can he make of it: thus, if the Church be full (ſo they blaſphemouſly call it) Chriſt being the only fulnes of the Church: And not ſome ignorant, prophane, and laſie Prieſt: That is a miſerable fulneſs, with which ſome Churches (ſo called) are filled; In ſuch a caſe of fulneſs the Lord Patron may ſell the reverſion for a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſum of money, to ſome one or other that hath ſent his Son to <hi>Oxford,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ambridge,</hi> to learn the Art of Logick, and Philoſophie; By which Craft he may know how to get his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving another day: And ſo the old Incumbent dying, this young Artiſt cometh to be preſented one, to enter and take poſſeſſion, and ſo to enjoy his portion his Father provided for him: The Gleab, the Tithes, and oblations; Together with the care, and cure of ſouls, and right of officiating to God, and man there, for this his Father bought, and purchaſed for
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:112863:13"/>
him, and who ſhall take it from him. But if the Church be empty, that is, of a Prieſt; then all his proprietie amounteth but to a ſhadow, unleſs it be ſure to put in one that being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to him, ſhall be ſure to ſerve him, and to forbear his luſts; or elſe marry his Kinſwoman, or his Wives Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, or Chambermaid: in conſideration of being preſented to be ſetled there: But can this work of darkneſs, and root of Iniquity, abide the light, or look in the face, without bluſhing the glorious light of the Goſpel that now ſhineth in this our horizon: Is not this property, a relick of the Merchandiſe of the great Whore, <hi>Revel:</hi> 18.13. that buyeth, and ſelleth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other wares the ſouls of men. What a ſad account have the moſt of theſe proprietors, theſe preſenters, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to make, for the many thouſand ſouls, that have peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by their means.</p>
            <p>But doth that Gentleman that made this one of his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as before, why he could fit no longer with his fellows to do the work of the Common-wealth, think indeed, and is it really his judgment, that a Parliament or Supream Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, have nothing to do to meddle with propriety; ſo as it ſhould be ſo great an offence, to meddle with the aytie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of preſentations: Sure upon conſideration he and thoſe Gentlemen that were ſo offended, cannot but think other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. That the Parliament may for a common good meddle with, and take away propriety, of a higher nature then Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations, and of higher, and more nigh concernment: eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when particular mens propriety is prejudicial to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good, ſo as the whole is profited by the loſs of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſons, he ſurely was one of them that gave his yea for the paſſing of the Bill for the monethly Aſſeſſement, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding it medled with propriety, even th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th part of the yearly Revenue, and Incomb of moſt men, and ſure he cannot but think they might do it in order to paſs like good, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any deſtroying propriety; Though many are as unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to part with it, as thoſe Gentlemen can be to part with their propriety of Preſentations.</p>
            <p>Was it a deſtroying propriety in his judgment, for the former Parliament to take into their hands, and to ſel away
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:112863:13"/>
the Lands of Biſhops, Deans, and Chapters, which they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed as their proprieties, with many rights and priviledges not inferior to Preſentations; which ſome of them had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver made forfeit, or of by-acting againſt the Parliament.</p>
            <p>Was the taking the fifth and twentieth part of Perſons Eſtates for the good of the whole, a deſtroying propriety, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſome ſaid ſo then, but we know what they were accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for ſo ſaying, no leſs then Malignants.</p>
            <p>Surely thoſe Gentlemen will not ſo ſay of the Inſtrument, or model of new Government, or thoſe that made it, as they do of thoſe that paſſed that Vote; Notwithſtanding it take two hundred thouſand pound <hi>per annum,</hi> for the carrying of it on.</p>
            <p>The former Parliament they did not reckon that they went beyond their Power, nor that they overthrew proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, when they paſſed the Act for the draining of the Fens; gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving away very much of the Lands, (the chiefeſt propriety) of the owner to the undertakers in order to Publick good.</p>
            <p>The fourth Vote, whereupon followed the Diſſolution of the Parliament, was that harmleſs Negative of not Comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Report of the Committee; Touching what they offered as the beſt way to eject ignorant, prophane, and ſcandalous Miniſters; and incouraging them that are good, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of which two things, and ſo an end of this diſcourſe; firſt of the proceed to it, and in the Debate of it; And then that which followed after it til the Houſe was Diſſolved: The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed was ſhortly thus: After the aforeſaid Vote had paſſed, and ſome of the Gentlemen of the Houſe were in readineſs to offer the Bill; The Committee for Tithes to countet-work, and keep that off as ſome thought, did on Monday morning offer this Repor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and many were for the taking of it on; others were againſt the medling with it at that time, ſome moving to have the Bill taken in concerning Preſentations, ſome to fall on things of more preſent concernment, as the Bill for uniting <hi>Scotland</hi> to <hi>England</hi> Reaſons were offered on every ſide, and after one of the clock the Houſe roſe, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing faſtned on: The next morning thoſe that were for the Report to be taken in the day before, moved again, and the other not oppoſing, it was taken in, but not without being
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:112863:14"/>
put to the Vote whether the Houſe would take it in, which was carried in the Affirmative, and ſo the Debate began, and continued day after day, til after one of the clock each day: The Speaker being aged, and not able to ſit longer: The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate was managed day by day with very great ſeriouſneſs, many Arguments and Scriptures being alledged.</p>
            <p>The Houſe being evenly poyſed, and great attendance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing given by the Members, waiting the time of the Vote; and though any Member might by the Rules of the Houſe have ſpoken every day ſo long as the Debate continued, yet ſuch was the modeſtie ſhewed, that hardly any on all the five dayes ſpake twice; very little of heat or paſſion being ſhewed all that time, onely one Gentleman or two that were for the Report, ſeeing themſelves and their partie ſo inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, flue out a little, complaining of the expence of Time, to have given a check to the going on of the Debate: But the Orders of the Houſe being called for, by ſome of the other ſide to the Speaker, he declared it to be the right of every one to be heard, and that the queſtion could not be put ſo long as any would ſpeak to it; withall thoſe Gentlemen were told of their reſtleſneſs to take on the Debate, and how now they wanted patience to wait the Iſſue of it: after three or four days a Member that was againſt the Report offered an Expedient, but was not accepted: At laſt on <hi>Saturday</hi> toward noon the queſtion grew neer as did alſo the end of the Parliament, ſome Members that were againſt 1ſte Report having not ſpoken, and aſſaying to ſpeak, were perſwaded to forbear, who onely gathered the Iſſue and reſult of the whole and left it to the Houſe, which was whether upon the whole this in the report was the beſt expedient for that end; which ſome on the other ſide that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for the Report perceiving the ſtreſs of the queſtion put there, moved that the word <hi>beſt</hi> might be put out; but it was not admitted, having been in the Report all the time of the Debate: ſo about one of the clock the Vote paſſed, and upon dividing the Houſe was carried in the Negative: A Debate of that nature and length in ſo great a Councell, hardly ever paſſed with ſuch ſoberneſs and little heat or paſſion: The buſineſs was in <hi>ſtatu quo,</hi> as to any ones being either
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:112863:14"/>
better or worſe, the report was laid aſide, for that the firſt part of it whereon the other part depended was rejected; to wit, that the beſt way to eject ignorant, prophane, and ſcandalous Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and to incourage them that are good, was by ſending cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Commiſſioners impowered to do it: as at full hath been put forth in Print already: There was at the paſſing this Vote 115. Members, whereof 54. were for the affirmative, and 56. for the negative; and two Gentlemen tellers for each ſide, and the Speaker, which make up that number.</p>
            <p>To go about to tell of the Arguments inſiſted on, from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and from Experience, and other Reaſons of a prudentiall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, would be too tedious; that this Vote that hurt no body ſhould occaſion ſuch wonderfull diſpleaſure, and out-cry every where is at leaſt wonderfull: If men were asked (as <hi>Micah</hi> was) what aileth them? they would hardly be able to tell, ſo well as hee did: is it not much, when as godly ſober men in diſcharge of their duty and truſt, for the glory of God, and good of their Countrey, ſhould leave their habitations, relations and injoyments, ſpend their time and meanes to ſerve their Countrey, and be ſo rewarded with ſcandalous and falſe reports, and to have judgement of high con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation paſſed on them upon hearſay, without the leaſt ſhew of proofe? Is it not much that men of learning, Leaders and Teachers of others, that would be eſteemed godly Orthodox Divines, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt, and Preachers of his Goſpel, ſhould be of ſuch a ſpirit and ſtrain ſo unlike Chriſt and the Goſpel, as to utter ſuch ſpeeches in Pulpits, and elſe-where? that they meaning thoſe that complyed not in the afore mentioned Vote, and voted in the other, were the arranteſt Rogues and Villaines that ever the earth bare: That their deſigne was worſe then the Gunpowder treaſon: That they would have deſtroyed the Magiſtracy and the Miniſtry, the Law and the Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> &amp;c. That it were well if one of ten of them were hanged up, and then there would be happy dayes: might not inquiry be made, what is the matter of this their ſo great rage and diſpleaſure; who hath hurt them or done them wrong? no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, but they would ſay: Oh they would have deſtroyed all the Miniſters, good aſwell as bad, and overthrown the Goſpel; for ſo they frequently ſay: heynous crimes indeed: but how doth it appeare? onely thus: they were againſt thoſe grievances of the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:112863:15"/>
Law, and Tithes, and would have had thoſe taken away; and they would not concur with the Report of the Committee in order to the ſetling of Tithes, that being in the bottome of the Report; ſo as by theſe mens Logick and concluſion, thoſe two great grievances of the Law and Tithes, (which theſe ſo reproched laboured to have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away) are the Magiſtracy and Miniſtry; the corrupt Law, or corruption of the Law, are the Magiſtracy; and Tithes they are the Miniſtry: yea more, the Goſpel alſo; but alas, Magiſtracy can ſtand without ſuch horrible corruptions of Law, and the Miniſtry with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Tithes, as it is in other Countries where there is neither of them. But the belly hath no ears, and therefore no more ſhall be ſayd.</p>
            <p>The afore mentioned Vote paſſing as it did, thoſe Gentlemen that miſſed of their expectations, and were croſſed of having their wils, greatly fearing, as it ſeemeth, it would goe ill with thoſe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt intereſts of the Lawyers and Clergy, which they indeavoured to ſupport: they took the Pet and were exceeding wroth divers of them, and that afternoone and the next day (being the Lords day, a day fittter for better imployment) they tooke Counſell with and among themſelves, holding Cabals, and there conſulting the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw and diſſolution of the Houſe, which was as they had decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to all the world the ſupreame Authority or Magiſtracy, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of the Common-wealth of England: is it not much that Gentlemen pretending ſo high to wiſdom and godlineſs, for miſſing the having their wills in a Vote carried in the Negative ſhould bee induced thereby preſently to take on ſuch deſperate Counſels and reſolves, and to draw others into them ignorantly, forgetting as it ſeemeth what they had ſolemly declared before God and all the world; to wit, that the Houſe was the Supreame Authority of the Common-wealth of England, which Common-wealth God had highly honoured, and made famous throughout the world; forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting alſo their ſeverity againſt malapart word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en in a Petition, becauſe it was the ſupreame Authority: What might ſuch Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, Reſolves and Actings merit by their owne Law? had they no charity in them towards their fellows, becauſe croſſed in that poore Vote? had they loſt or laid aſide the feare of God, that they could thus venture to overthrow Magiſtracy even the greateſt in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, the Parliament and ſupream Authority, to the indan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering the whole Cauſe? The Members that they were ſo angry
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:112863:15"/>
with, and have ſo reproached as being againſt Magiſtracy and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, becauſe that poore negative Vote was carried againſt their wills may ſay to them as <hi>Jehu</hi> ſaid to the Rulers of Samaria, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 109 <hi>ye be righteous:</hi> Indeed they voted in the affirmative in thoſe former Votes, and in the negative in theſe laſt Votes concerning Triers: but who conſulted and put in practiſe the overthrow and diſſolution of the Parliament, and Supreame Authority of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth of England? having ſlept upon their Counſels, they are of the ſame minde ſtill, and addreſs themſelves to put it in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, riſing early and comming betime to put in practiſe their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, which was to diſſolve and put to an end the Parliament of the Common-wealth of England in their own eſteem: and being come, they feared not to begin with prayer to God the ſearcher of hearts, and then proceed to declare their purpoſe and the reaſons of it, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing load upon their fellows in way of blame, that were leſſe guilty of evill then themſelves, uttering words that could not but aſtoniſh any good ſoule of a dying Parliament; charging their fellowes that were for the removing of the great grievances of the Law and Tithes, that they followed their owne wills; nay, their own luſts, words not fit to be ſpoken in a free Counſell, and that might have been more truly ſaid of themſelves: when thoſe of the other ſide that knew nothing of their deſigne offered to ſpeake, telling them it was no time to debate; only one good Patriot of thoſe that were zealous for the remove of thoſe afore mentioned great grievances, ſtood up and got audience, ſpeaking againſt what they had moved, intimating the good Bils that were in readineſs to be brought in for the Peoples good; and proteſting before God, Angels and Men, againſt what they had moved; and others of the ſame party ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ready to do the like, who called to the Speaker to be heard thoſe Gentlemen without hearing their fellows, or admitting the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, or putting the queſtion, roſe up out of their places to be gone, and others in ſimplicity followed, as once many did after <hi>Abſolom,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.11. not knowing any thing at all, but how they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed their Truſt the world may judge.</p>
            <p>The Speaker forgetting the duty of his place, though hee was earneſtly called unto to keep the Chayr, hee left it, and the Serjeant as if he had been of Counſell, took up the Mace, and carried it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, though he was ſpoken unto to the contrary, as in like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:112863:16"/>
did the chiefe Clerk: and thus in an irruptions way going out of the Houſe without any Adjournment or Vote, left ſitting thirty four or thirty five Members in the Houſe; whether thoſe that ſo went away were a greater or a leſſer number, as is more likely, but is hard to be determined, though it be thought by ſome, there were not ſeventy ſo early in the Houſe. Thoſe that went out of the houſe going toward White-hall, met ſome comming to the Houſe, who ſeeing them goe in that maner, thought they had Adjourned thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſo went along with them; others they ſent for up and down where they could finde them, to come to them to the Horſe Chamber, where they were: Thoſe in the Houſe immediatly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took themſelves to conſider what they had to doe, being ſo deſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of their Fellowes: and telling over their number, they found themſelves but thirty four, or thirty five, which could not make a Houſe, forty being the leaſt number that might act in a Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary way. And as they were going to conſider among themſelves, a Colonell and Lievetenant Colonell of the Army, entred the Houſe, and deſired them to depart: the Members deſired them to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw, for that they as Members of Parliament, had warrant to bee there, and if they had warrant to put them out, they wiſhed them to ſhew it; but not many words paſſed, but they went backe and opened the doors, and brought in the ſouldiers with their Muskets, and ſo then the Gentlemen roſe and went out; which was done before the other were halfe way at White-hall: and ſome ſo put out of the Houſe, went after to White-hall to ſee what they were there doing, and found them in the Horſe Chamber, preparing a writing of ſurrender of their power back into his hands, from whom they had received it. If they had been his Counſell, and not Legiſlators, or a Parliament, much might have been in it; it was three or fowre lines written in fowr or ſix ſeverall papers, that ſo the Gentlemen might the more eaſily read and ſee what it was, which then the Clerk ingroſſed in Parchment, and then they ſigned it, by ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing their names ſo many as would. Firſt the Speaker, and then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther according to their quality. It may bee wondered at, that ſo great a power ſhould be paſſed by ſo low and little an Inſtrument. Some Gentlemen went three or fowre dayes after, and ſet their hands to it: they that ſubſcribed it, did it on ſeverall grounds and reaſons: ſome did it knowingly to diſſolve the Houſe, before diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:112863:16"/>
by the Souldiers, and their diſorderly going away, which they had plotted and reſolved before: ſome becauſe ſome eminent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of their party did it before them, expecting by that meanes to have been rid of ſome of the other party at the leaſt, and they to have been continued in power without them, wherein they were deceived, and not a little vexed: ſome therein looked no further then at their owne quiet, and to bee rid of a troubleſome imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: ſome that they might not be thought lovers of power and dignity; and ſome out of weakneſs, and feare of the loſs of ſome worldly injoyment, which they have ſufficiently repented and been ſorry for ſince.</p>
            <p>But how weak an Act, and contrary to their truſt it was for thoſe that profeſſed themſelves to be Legiſlators, had made Lawes and levied mony by way of Tax upon the people as the Parliament and Supream Authority of the Common-wealth of England, as cloathed with their power, ſo eaſily, and without their knowledge or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent whom they pretended to repreſent in Parliament, to give up, or give away their power which was none of theirs to give, but at the moſt to uſe for their good; to doe it without debate or conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, in ſo weighty a caſe; to do it when the Parliament was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved by themſelves and the Souldiers, and they but in the capacity of ſingular perſons; to give it up, as much as in them lay, into the hands of one ſingle perſon, and that againſt a ſtanding Law then in being, not repealed: was it not in effect to render all the people of England ſlavs: as would eaſily be granted by their own party, if they had ſo delivered to <hi>Charles Stuart:</hi> were ever men ſo weake, raſh, and inconſiderate, ſo out-witted, or carried away with paſſion and ſpleen againſt their fellowes, becauſe they indeavoured to remove thoſe grievances of Tithes and the Law which the people of this Nation groan exceedingly under? But might not the validity of this act of theirs be queried? if a Jury ſhould give up their Verdict ſo, or deliver over their truſt to others, would it be counted valid? but ſo it was, and ſo they did: and ſo an end of that Parliament that ſate five months and three dayes as the ſupream Power of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth of England, whom God preſerve.</p>
            <p>And ſo an end of this Relation and Diſcourſe, with the calling to minde the ſaying of the Pſalmiſt, 11. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.7. <hi>If the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be deſtroyed, what can the Righteous doe? The righteous Lord loveth righteouſneſs, his countenance doth behold the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
